טוב *Tov*, today's דף daf *daf* is דף daf כ"ג *daf Chaf
Gimmel*, where in the middle we've begun the second פרק *perek*, and
the second פרק *perek* starts with a continuation of things you can't
do with the surrounding non-Jews slash pagans, and now specifically getting into
sort of sexual areas. We sort of touched on it before when
the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* said that you don't sell בהמה דקה *behema
daka*, or there's certain practices of whether you sell בהמה דקה *behema
daka* to non-Jews, and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said that that has
to do with the concern of bestiality. Here it speaks about it
more explicitly, I mean about leaving animals in a stall
owned by non-Jews,
and then we'll get on to other parts about it about people,
about women, a woman shouldn't be in ייחוד yichud, *yichud* because of
rape, a man shouldn't be in ייחוד yichud *yichud* because of
murder, and of course the issue comes up, like this is getting
to be pretty
bad, pretty bad in terms of how it's, until now it was
like a concern
about them doing pagan worship, okay, they did pagan worship. It was
a concern
about maybe certain types of animals that were dangerous, but like we
as Jews shouldn't be owning them anyway, maybe don't sell them weapons
or build things because okay, they actually did persecute and prosecute Jews
and so on, so like all that type of stuff. Now whether
you still interpret that as the rule or as the exception or
whatever, but like that stuff we can I think understand that that
somewhat corresponds to their experience. Other things that we saw about selling
animals or selling land was that because of a certain הלכות *halachot*
about like work on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat* and using the animal on
שבת *Shabbat*, לא תחנם *lo tichunem*, or was it an idea of
more the sort of societal reality of trying to strengthen the presence
of the Jewish presence in the land of Israel. Anyway, all those
things were like relatively understandable. But here it's getting to be pretty
harsh, and on the one hand, the idea about about women and
men being in ייחוד yichud. *yichud* with them, so look, I don't
know how to respond to that, were they what, I have no
idea what the actual reality
was, but at what stage if there's sort of do you take
a few, look, it goes like it touches of like racism, somebody
who says like if I'm on the street alone and I see
a person of a certain race or
whatever, I'm scared, and probably a lot of people are scared and
they don't admit it because of certain types of ways in which
we project onto the other.
And so, I mean, but at least I don't know, I guess
my feeling is that at least I'm sympathetic to that because I
can understand that there were
actual cases in which Jews were murdered or raped. Although murder is
interesting, like I understood that it comes from, came from the oppression
that came from the Roman government. I don't know why necessarily this
reality, this assumption that every Roman is looking or every pagan is
looking for an opportunity to kill us, right? But like I'm saying,
I think we sort of know the same type of things happens
when we sort of project things on the other. So anyway, so
the rape and the murder issue I don't know how much that's
based on fact, but at least I guess I'm a little sympathetic
to the idea that if there is a fear and a concern
for one's life, then you want to be protective, you want to
be careful about those types of things. I mean rape and murder
do happen. So if you see the larger outside world as hostile
and you see your community as all nice and friendly, you're going
to be more careful when you go out into the into the
outside world. But the whole area of the bestiality I think is
something that I think we can all understand is like seems a
little like overboard, this assumption that they're looking for every opportunity to
have an act, to do an act of bestiality with an animal,
and our animal, that's of course an extreme statement. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*
even says on that like I don't know where the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is getting this idea from, it was one statement, it gets
incorporated into the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but certainly the dominant idea anyway,
but that's part in particular an extreme. So look, I don't know
what to say other than that it really seems to be, you
see the outside world and you see the other, the other people
out there as hostile, and you wind up like projecting a lot
of stuff on them. So I don't really know what to say,
but it is a challenging גמרא Gemara *Gemara* to read. So anyway,
so yeah, but the problem I think more comes from, I guess
I would I guess the point I would make is that the
problem bothers me less that rather at a particular time had these
concerns and wanted to be protective of their people and so on,
like okay, you sort of understand where that comes from, but what
bothers me is that when it gets sort of then incorporated not
just into הלכה halacha, *halacha*, because exactly, exactly, because as a matter
of הלכה halacha *halacha*, like they probably didn't keep this anyway, I'll
say a minute, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says how come we're not מקפיד
*makpid* on this nowadays, like
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says. so as I say. But, you know, but
it's less about the הלכה, Halacha but it's more about, like, the
rabbinic mindset. You know, we keep on learning this in the ישיבות
yeshivot and teaching it and it becomes internalized. And then, you know,
where you might have seen the non-Jews around you in a different
light, now you're internalizing this idea that there's so crazy, you know,
aberrant sexuality. I mean, it's not unusual that you project on the
other who's seen as threat or hostile or whatever, you know, aberrant
sexuality, right? But then this becomes, you know, winds up informing a
way in which people will just look at whatever whoever the non-Jews
are at their time. So, it really is a big challenge, like,
you know, reading this. Again, I said, not so much maybe understanding
it historically, I can think it's like sympathetic
how these things might grow up, these understandings, but
but understanding then how it continues to, like, influence, you know, later
ways of thinking. So, anyway, that's sort of where we're at. I
will let's take a look as we continue the גמרא Gemara and
then I'll go back and reference the idea that תוספות Tosafot says
that, like, this was not really practiced in his time. What?
No, they're all looking at me.
Yeah, like, what is the matter, Michal? Like, why did you teach
us that גמרא Gemara yesterday?
Okay, anyway, I don't think you want to have a conversation about
this now.
Yes,
that's correct. If you if you want to—okay, if you have other
thoughts about it, I'm happy to talk after. Okay, appreciate
that.
All right, leave it.
Okay, okay, fine.
Okay, רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, let's start with the first line on
כ"ג עמוד א'. chaf gimmel amud aleph. So, the question was,
was that the—what do you call it?—the משנה Mishnah: says you don't
sell the—you know, you don't leave these animals in the stalls—and the
ברייתא Baraita said that you can buy animals for sacrifices to use
for sacrifices. Well, why aren't we concerned that they did these acts
of bestiality? So, the answer yesterday was
because they only do it to our animals, not to their animals,
because their animals they're afraid that they will become sterile. And then
the גמרא Gemara went through a whole description about certain merit about
male or female or whatever, okay, or weaken them or whatever. So,
let's take a look now at a different answer. רבינא אמר לא
קשיא, Ravina amar lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא לכתחילה הא בדיעבד.
ha lechatchila ha bedieved.
The difference is whether at the outset are we concerned, don't act
in certain ways because we're concerned it will happen; however, we're not
concerned that it did happen. If we were to buy an animal
from them means making an assertion that it did happen and that
we're not going to say. We're concerned that it will happen. Now,
what's the difference between לכתחילה lechatchila and בדיעבד? bedieved? So, often we
think that the difference between לכתחילה lechatchila and בדיעבד bedieved is, like,
בדיעבד bedieved is, like, you know, it's like there will be a
loss. Like, it's one thing to say don't do this, it's another
thing to say, 'Oh, now it already happened and are you going
to tell me I'm going to have to, like, not use my
animal, you know, get rid of it?' Like, don't cook in a
certain pot. Oh, you already cooked in it, don't do the food
out. Okay, because of the issue of the loss. But here there's
not an issue of a loss. Here it's like telling me I
can go ahead and לכתחילה lechatchila buy an animal from a non-Jew
to use as a sacrifice because because whatever happened already happened. Or
I'm not concerned that it already happened. Well, okay, but there's no
loss, so I'll just go buy it from a Jew. Like, it's
not clear why בדיעבד bedieved should make a difference. And I think
that the difference here is because, you know, because it's still לכתחילה
lechatchila from my perspective whether I'm choosing to buy it or not.
The issue here, the בדיעבד, bedieved, I think is what the גמרא
Gemara says in גיטין Gittin about שמא ימות חיישינן שמא מת לא
חיישינן. shema yamut chayshinan shema met lo chayshinan. That, that if somebody
sends a, you know, a גט get and says, 'Give this גט
get to my wife,' and then it's being given and he's a
thousand miles away, the the husband, you can give it and you
don't—you're not assume that the guy's already dead. Okay, you can give
it and assume the guy's still alive. But if he says, 'Give
this גט get to my wife and it should take place, it
should take effect a minute before I die,' you can't give it.
Because you have to be afraid that right now is a minute
before he dies. What's the difference? Why do I have to—why can't
I be afraid—I don't have to be afraid that he's dead, but
I have to be afraid it's a minute before he dies? Okay,
and the basic difference is is that is that everybody is, like,
going to die. So to say he might die in the next
minute is a reasonable thing to be concerned about. But to make
an assertion that he is definitely dead, right, is a different type
of a thing. It's going against, like if you want to use
הלכתי halakhic terminology, it's going against his חזקת חיים. chezkat chayim. He
has a status of being alive. And therefore, we're not going to
now assert that that status changed and he was dead. But it's
to say that he will die in another minute, in another hour,
that's possible and actually it's natural. People, especially if they're on their
deathbed, die, you know, but anyway everybody eventually dies. So I think
that's the difference here. To worry about the future, to say don't
leave your animal, who knows what's going to happen with it if
you leave it, okay, that's like that we will do, we'll be
concerned about— possible future things. But when I'm coming to buy an
animal and to assert, "I'm going to assume something happened to this
animal," okay, that's I'm not going to do. So that's what רבינא
Ravina says. לא קשיא הא לכתחילה הא בדיעבד. Lo kashya, ha lechatchila,
ha bedieved. Now the גמרא Gemara says, ומנאן תימא, uminan teima, how
do you know דשאני בין לכתחילה בין לבדיעבד, dishani bein lechatchila bein
lebedieved, that we make a distinction between לכתחילה lechatchila and בדיעבד? bedieved?
דתנן, Ditnan, we taught in the משנה: Mishnah לא תתייחד אשה עמהם
מפני שחשודים על העריות. Lo tisyached isha imahem mipnei shechashudim al ha-arayos.
Our משנה mishna, says a woman should not be in private with
the non-Jews because she's suspect of they'll be raped, okay. ורמינהו, Veraminu,
and I'll ask you on this: האשה שנחבשה בידי עובדי כוכבים אם
על ידי ממון מותרת לבעלה. Ha'isha shenechebesha bidei ovdei kochavim, im al
yedei mamon, muteres l'baalah.
A woman who was taken captive by the non-Jews and she's taken
captive because the husband owes them money and the husband isn't paying
up. So what they do is they seize the wife, they kidnap
the wife and they say, "You want your wife back? Give us
the thousand dollars that you owe." Okay, and then he pays up
the money, the wife comes back, she's permissible to her husband, we
can assume she has not been raped. תוספות Tosafot makes the point
that we're talking even about the wife of a כהן. Kohen. It's
not a question about whether she was willing or not. A wife
of a ישראל, Yisrael, even if she was raped, I mean God
forbid, she would still be permissible to her husband. But here it's
even the wife of a כהן, Kohen, we do not assume that
she was
raped, okay. על ידי נפשות אסורה לבעלה. Al yedei nefashos, asura l'baalah.
So,
but if she was seized because of, you know, that for because
like the husband was liable like the, you know, the death penalty
or whatever, you know, or so that type of a case where
there's an issue of actually let me just check רש"י Rashi here,
here.
No, there's no רש"י Rashi on על ידי נפשות. al yedei nefashos.
But anyway the basic point, moment, yeah, no, I'm sorry, שנתחייבה הריגה,
shenecheyeiva hariga, yeah, that's what I thought, I'm sorry, that's why I
wanted to check it. No, not the husband. If she's captured because
she is somehow liable in the death penalty, they say that she's
liable to be executed, then she's forbidden to her husband. And this
would be even her husband who's a ישראל Yisrael and not a
כהן. Kohen. And the reason is is that if she's taken and
she's under threat of death, she's afraid that they'll execute her, so
then she might do anything in order to get out of that,
you know, and she might actually, you know, agree to have, you
know, to choose, I mean obviously it's under a threat of force,
you know, it's interesting that we consider that רצון ratzon and not
אונס ones if she's doing it in order to save her life
and obviously why don't we consider the whole setting one of like
a threat of violence and a type of an אונס, ones, but
that which is a very important question, especially in discussions nowadays about
those types of issues. But anyway, but that she will choose to
sort of trade, you know, her sex, you know, sex with herself
for her life, and therefore it'll be a case that we find
as רצון ratzon and she'll be forbidden even to her husband ישראל.
Yisrael. So in the first case, right? Right, exactly, the last case.
So in the first case we're not concerned even of rape and
she's permitted to a כהן, Kohen, and the second case we're concerned
about willing, you know, acts in order to save her life and
that which we'll call רצון ratzon and that she's forbidden even to
her husband ישראל. Yisrael. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, now
what's the difference? אלא לאו, Ela lav, so why is this true?
Don't we say that she can't go in private because we're afraid
that she'll be raped? And here we're saying that if she was
seized by them for monetary purposes she can go back to her
husband. Why aren't we said, you know, even a כהן, Kohen, why
don't we say she can't go back to her husband because we're
afraid she was raped? So what's the difference? אלא לאו שמע מינה
שאני לך בין לכתחילה לבדיעבד. Ela lav shema mina shani lach bein
lechatchila lebedieved. You make a distinction between don't do certain things because
you're afraid what might happen in the future, she might be raped,
don't go in private, but if she was taken we're not going
to assert that she was raped. Okay, now before we see what
the גמרא's Gemara. answer is, there's still a very big difference here.
The big difference is is that
to
assert that the animal had an act of bestiality done to it
would just mean saying don't buy it for a קרבן, korban, buy
something else, there's not a big consequence. To assert that the woman
was raped means that you're going to have to tell her husband
the כהן Kohen he has to divorce her, there's a pretty huge
consequence. It's a real בדיעבד, bedieved, not just that the act was
already done but like the fallout is huge. So therefore, like it
might be one thing to say we're not going to be concerned
about it in that case because we don't want to break up
the marriage, that's not a sufficient explanation that we're not going to
be concerned about it to say don't buy this animal for a
קרבן. korban. Okay, but anyway the גמרא's Gemara not looking at that
and the גמרא Gemara. just says the rule here is we're concerned
about possible things, possible things that might happen in the future, we're
not concerned about things that might have already happened. So the גמרא
Gemara says, well one minute, says the גמרא. Gemara מי מאי, Mi
mai, who says that's the basic line of difference, whether it's about
the future or the
past? דילמא לעולם אימא לך Dilma l'olam eima lach אפילו בדיעבד נמי
לא, afilu bedieved nami lo, that even after the fact under normal
circumstances we would, I'm sorry, under normal circumstances we would,
the "lo" is funny, we would, anyway, under normal circumstances we would
be concerned even after the fact and therefore we should be concerned
about not buying the animals and under normal circumstances we'd be concerned
about this woman that she was raped. והכא היינו טעמא, Vehacha hainu
taama, here's the reason why in... In this case we're not concerned
she was raped even though normally we would be, דמיסתפי d'mistapai משום
הפסד ממונא. mishum hefsed mamona. This guy who sees this woman is
trying to just get his money from the husband and he's afraid
that if he rapes this woman, the husband might decide, look if
you rape my wife, mean, look it's very sad to speak about
these realities but you know, but these were sometimes, you know, the
ways certain realities were in the ancient world. Oh, you rape my
wife, so she's damaged goods, I don't want her back, so I'm
not going to pay you the money I owe you. So because
he doesn't want to lose that money, so therefore the captor is
going to be on his good behavior and not rape her. Okay,
but under other circumstances we would be afraid it would be concerned
and Tosfos actually gives a good case. Tosfos says there's three two
scenarios here, but there's a third not mentioned. Scenario one is she's
seized in order to get money from the husband. Scenario two is
she's seized because she's liable the death penalty and then we say
that she might even like, you know, do it ברצון. b'ratzon. But
what about scenario three says Tosfos? Scenario three is she's seized not
because of money and not because of the death penalty, she's just
like סתם stam seized and taken captive. So that case we would
also be concerned, we would be concerned maybe it was רצון, ratzon,
but we'd certainly be concerned it was raped. Okay, so that the
only case that we're not concerned that it's rape is this case
of ממון, mamon, is this case of trying to get money out
of the husband, and that's what the Gemara is saying. So the
Gemara is saying is we would be concerned after the fact. There's
a special reason here we're not concerned because of the special case
that he's trying to get money out of the husband. Okay, and
now the Gemara continues,
וכדאיתא u'chedeisa you should know דקתני סיפא d'katani seifa we talked at
the end, היינו דעל ידי נפשות hainu d'al yedei nefashos אסורה לבעלה.
asura l'ba'alah. If it's for the, if it's, because of for like
for her life, then she is forbidden to her husband and that
clearly shows that when there's not the aspect of money that is
protecting, then they are going to engage, in you know, in sex,
and whether rape or whether willfully based on the circumstances, ותו לא
מידי, v'su lo midi, and there is really nothing else to talk
about in this conversation, okay says the Gemara. That we consider to
be end of conversation, ותו לא מידי. v'su lo midi. That we
consider that to be very clear that what's going on in that
issue about the difference between ממון mamon and נפשות nefashos is not
that we're not concerned after the fact. Again as Tosfos says, if
it was neither ממון mamon or נפשות, nefashos, we would be concerned
after the fact that she had been raped. Okay, so therefore the
only reason there it's not is because he doesn't want to lose
the money the husband owes him, so you cannot use that as
a basis for your argument that we're only concerned about these animals
because they might be raped, they might be acts of bestiality, but
we're not concerned after the fact. We would be concerned if we're
concerned it might happen, we would be concerned it will happen. Now
I want to pause for a moment and talk about another example
that Tosfos says how do we do this? So we'll get back
to the question of how do we leave our animals in the
stables? But Tosfos here has a more important question which is very
relevant to the Ashkenazi reality, which is, if you take a look
at Tosfos, ותו לא מידי, v'su lo midi, okay, you look at
that Tosfos, he says, he says like this: פירש דודאי הפסד ממון
שאני. peireish d'vadai hefsed mamon shani. אבל ייחוד דעלמא, aval yichud d'alma,
but if it was just if it wasn't about the money aspect
that was protecting her, as it were, then we would be afraid
she was raped. Now Tosfos says under what circumstances would we be
afraid that she was raped after the fact? It sounds like once
she was in private with a non-Jew. Every... so אבל ייחוד דעלמא,
aval yichud d'alma,
he says,
where were we? אימא דאסור אף דיעבד. eima d'asur af d'ieved. And
then Tosfos says, תימה! teima! But wait, this is astounding. אם כן
לא הנחת בת לאברהם אבינו, im kein lo hinachta bas l'Avraham Avinu,
אשת כהן eishes Kohen יושבת תחת בעלה. yosheves tachas ba'alah. Then any
woman who's married to a Kohen will should be forbidden to her
husband. Why? Because again it's a concern of rape not of willing.
He says, דאי אפשר שלא תתייחד עם שום עובד כוכבים שעה אחת.
d'ee efshar shelo tisyached im shum oved kochavim sha'a achas. It's impossible
in our society that there won't be a time where a woman
will be in private with a non-Jewish man, and you're saying like
what? Why is that impossible? And this is really speaks to a
fascinating reality, that in Ashkenaz, although we tend to think in Ashkenaz,
you know, that women were like, you know, were actually... no, that's
in Sefard, excuse me. Anyway, in Ashkenaz, women were actually more active
in the outside society and even in business and so on, not
just in social spheres, in business spheres, etc.
And therefore if you have to deal out in the business world
and you're going and you know, there's like what we're dealing with
right now, you know, you sometimes have to take a meeting in
private. So Tosfos actually says, right? Because if you were dealing with
like Sefarad where the women are all at this time all staying
at home, right, and never leaving sort of the domestic sphere, what
do you mean it's impossible that they should ever be, no, there'll
always be that a woman will be in private with a non-Jew
at some time? Like what are you talking about? But this actually
speaks to the reality that women were actually much more involved in
the public social sphere and also in the business world in Ashkenaz.
Okay, and that sort of the ramifications of that are felt in
a lot of פסקים psakim in Ashkenaz. For example, Tosfos says the
Gemara says that a woman doesn't recline on, doesn't do הסיבה haseiba
on the Pesach Seder because like, you know, because she's seen as
like she. she wouldn't quite have the status to do הסבה haseiba
in the presence of her husband. Okay, but גמרא Gemara. says, but
if she's an אשה חשובה, isha hashuvah, but if she's a woman
of status, you know, then, you know, where she's not seen as
totally sort of submissive to her husband, then she does הסבה. haseiba.
And then תוספות Tosafot says, all of our women are אשה חשובה,
isha hashuvah, are נשים חשובות. nashim hashuvot. What he means is that
their status in society is, you know, it's still a patriarchy, but
still, you know, they have a much higher status in society than
they had in the past. So this, this whole אשכנזי Ashkenazi reality
of women's status is felt in a number of places. And here
תוספות Tosafot says there's a reality that women are taking private meetings
with non-Jews, okay, and then if she's married to a כהן, Kohen,
why don't we just assume she was raped? Okay, which is what
it sounds like from the גמרא. Gemara So let's see the answer.
He says, וכיון דליכא הפסד ממון, v'keivan d'leika hefsed mamon,
and since like it's not like he's afraid he's going to lose
money as a result, the non-Jew, חיישינן, chaishinan, we should be afraid.
ויש לומר דאין זה אלא דחוי בעלמא. v'yesh lomar d'ein zeh ela
dichuy b'alma.
The גמרא Gemara is just saying like, I could get out of
this proof. כלומר מהכא לא תוכיח. kolomar mehacha lo tochiah. ומכל מקום
דברי רבינא אמת. u'mikal makom divrei Ravina emet. That's pretty pleasant. In
the end, really רבינא Ravina was right. We're not afraid after the
fact, but the גמרא Gemara's is just saying this isn't a proof
to it. That's pretty interesting. ואחר כך חזר בו, v'achar kach chazar
bo, וסבר ומידי, v'savar u'midei, ועוד יש לומר, v'od yesh lomar,
here's תוספות'ס Tosafot's real answer. דאפילו מאן דאסר ייחוד מועט, d'afilu man
d'asar yichud muat,
if somebody's in a private meeting for an hour or whatever, that's
not what we're talking about. There maybe you shouldn't do it לכתחילה,
l'chatchila, there still our משנה, mishna. notice תוספות Tosafot isn't justifying how
they violate the משנה. mishna The משנה mishna says you're not supposed
to do it לכתחילה. l'chatchila. He's only worried about the after the
fact. Okay, but he says just being in private for a period
of time, we're not going to be concerned about rape. דדווקא נשבית
שאני, d'davka nishbis shani,
if you're taken captive, that's a different story. לפי שהיא מסורה בידו,
lefi shehi mesurah b'yado, because then, you know, he's totally under his
control. He takes her back to wherever he is. She's at his,
you know, she's at his complete mercy. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says
you go into a business meeting for an hour, you're not supposed
to do it, the משנה mishna says you don't do ייחוד, but
we're not going to be concerned after the fact. Okay? Taken captive
is a very different story. So fascinating תוספות Tosafot that reflects on
the reality number one that women... it would be regular, like it's
widespread that women are like will have opportunity, you know, are sometimes
in ייחוד with non-Jews, okay, and then he explains after the fact
it's not a problem, we're not assumed about rape. He does not
bother to explain how it gets around the prohibition in the משנה
mishna that you're not even supposed to do it לכתחילה. l'chatchila. Okay?
So very interesting תוספות Tosafot's in terms of...
So what do you
do about that at business? We try not to have ייחוד. I
mean, you know, actually nowadays we're in a much better situation because
of the larger awareness in society. You know, you have a door
should be open, whatever the case might be. There's actually ways of
addressing it. Glass door. Glass door, yeah.
At the end of this note that just discussing what you just
explained, it says "still an animal is deemed unfit to sacrifice even
if it was briefly stable within an idol."
What? The note that I have, not...
Yeah.
It says that even with that explanation of תוספות Tosafot about the
women, it said when talking about an animal... Yeah.
Right. The animal still in the end they assume an animal is
different, right, exactly. Okay, so now let's go back to the גמרא.
Gemara So that's one answer of why you can buy it for
a קרבן korban but not put it... it's a difference of לכתחילה
l'chatchila and בדיעבד, b'diavad, but the גמרא Gemara, seems to reject that.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. רבי פדת אמר, Rabbi Padat
amar, Rabbi Padat says, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא
רבי אליעזר והא רבנן. ha Rabbi Eliezer v'ha Rabbanan. It's a difference
between רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן. Rabbanan. דתנן גבי פרת
חטאת, d'tenan gabi parat chatat, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, meaning
there's a debate whether we're concerned whether non-Jews do acts of bestiality.
So this whole thing which we were sort of having all this
angst about at the beginning, okay, the גמרא's Gemara going to actually
say maybe this is a debate between רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
the רבנן Rabbanan about whether we actually have this concern about non-Jews.
Meaning our משנה mishna is דעת יחיד? da'at yachid?
Yeah, our משנה mishnah would only be the position of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן Rabbanan would say we're not concerned that
non-Jews do acts of bestiality.
Why are we translating עכו"ם akum as non-Jews?
Well, okay, because, well, okay, first of because the original גרסא girsa
is גוי, goy, not עכו"ם. akum. עכו"ם akum is a censored word.
If one way of dealing with this גמרא Gemara is to say
somehow we're only concerned that idolaters and pagans did these acts.
It's not exactly clear to me why we would assume that there's
a connection between the fact that they're pagans and that they do
these acts, unless you're thinking that they're doing these acts as some
type of pagan ritual, but there's nothing that sort of that sort
of indicates that. What?
Especially לגבי כותי l'gabi Kuti because he accepts the תורה שבכתב. Torah
shebichtav.
Right, and he said there's a lot
of non-Jews around that accept...
Right.
So I mean what you could, sure. When I'm saying non-Jews, right,
when I'm saying non-Jews, I'm describing when the, what
meaning,
when
the רבנן Rabbanan were saying this originally, were they intending to say
"Oh, only for idolaters are we concerned about bestiality, but non-idolaters we're
not," or were they sort of perceiving the larger non-Jewish world this
way? I don't see any
reason... indication in the גמרא, Gemara that they're linking these concerns with
the fact that they're idolaters. But if what you want to say
is, whatever the גמרא Gemara thought about the non-Jews of its day,
if you actually have like you take a המאירי Meiri approach and
say, if you're dealing with a reality of non-Jews who are known
to live moral lives and so on then none of this would
apply, yeah, then that I would agree with. You could certainly say
that the גמרא Gemara's assumed that this was true of the non-Jews
of its day, but and maybe they saw those non-Jews and maybe
it was actually based on some facts, they saw those non-Jews as
immoral and as doing all these types of things, but when you're
dealing with non-Jews that are moral the way the phrase the המאירי
Meiri uses is גדורים בדרכי הדתות והנימוסים, gedurim b'darkei hadatot vehanimusim, or
especially if you want to say if they're a בן נח Ben
Noach and they're מקבל שבע מצוות בני נח mekabel sheva mitzvot bnei
Noach or whatever that would put them in a different category. Sure,
that you could definitely say that. So I think there's a difference
between what we're thinking the rabbis were saying at their time, were
they looking at the phenomenon at their time and saying what we're
saying here is about the pagans, we're not saying it about these
people here that are non-Jews but happen to not worship idols. So
I don't think they were making that distinction in this הלכה, okay,
but whether it continues to apply in the future to all non-Jews
is obviously a different story.
Just from the text because they exclude the כותי. Kuti. But the
כותי Kuti is Jewish.
The גמרא Gemara assumes, yeah, the גמרא Gemara assumes, yeah, that the
There's certain things that the גמרא Gemara doesn't yet deal with, it
doesn't have Christianity the way we have Christianity.
Right, and it doesn't deal with בני נח Bnei Noach and it
doesn't right. So that has allowed תוספות Tosafot's in a lot of
cases, תוספות's Tosafot answers have usually been more local, the המאירי's Meiri's
general answer to why we don't do all this stuff is that
all this about was the ancient pagans, and even if it wasn't
concerns related to idolatry, it was an assumption that those ancient pagans
had all this immorality were immoral etc. But nowadays dealing with Christians
and Muslims or whatever he says it's all different. That's what the
המאירי Meiri says. So the המאירי Meiri says exactly that. Yes, okay,
but I'm trying I'm translating it not in terms of what I
think the contemporary relevance is but what I think that the גמרא's
Gemara the גמרא Gemara is saying.
Right, but again remember עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim is the censored thing
that came in in like the middle ages. The original גמרא Gemara
was גוי. goy. So I mean it's so I could similarly censor
it but I want to be honest with what the גמרא Gemara.
is saying. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
so לא קשיא הא רבי אליעזר והא רבנן, lo kashya ha Rabi
Eliezer veha rabanan, is this question about whether we're concerned that they
do acts of bestiality, I could just say זה zeh and leave
it generic, okay, that they do acts of bestiality is a debate
between רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer and the רבנן. rabanan. דתנן גבי פרת
חטאת רבי אליעזר אומר אין ניקחת מן עובדי כוכבים, d'tnan gabei parat
chatat Rabi Eliezer omer ein nikachat min ovdei kochavim, you don't buy
an animal for פרה אדומה parah adumah from the non-Jews because you're
afraid that they did this act of bestiality, וחכמים מתירין, vechachamim matirin,
the חכמים chachamim allow it. מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי, mai lav beha
kamiflegi, this must be the debate. רבי אליעזר סבר חיישינן לרביעה, Rabi
Eliezer savar chayshinan l'reviah, we're concerned of acts of bestiality. רבנן סברי
לא חיישינן לרביעה, rabanan savri lo chayshinan l'reviah, we're not concerned of
these acts. Okay, so therefore it's great and therefore the משנה Mishna
that says don't put them in the inn is going like רבי
אליעזר Rabi Eliezer and the ברייתא braita that says that you can
buy them for קרבנות korbanot is going like the רבנן rabanan that
you're not concerned for acts of bestiality. So I just want to
pause for a minute and say that תוספות Tosafot, on the previous
דף said how come we leave our animals in the inns of
with non-Jews and or whatever the stables, and תוספות's Tosafot's basic answer
was we rule like this final answer in the גמרא Gemara that
it's a debate between the חכמים chachamim and רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer
whether we're concerned that they do these acts of bestiality and we
rule like the חכמים chachamim and therefore we're not afraid that they
do those acts. So therefore according to תוספות Tosafot at least it
works out nicely that he basically says by adopting this answer of
the גמרא Gemara we're able to bracket these concerns as a position
of רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer and to say that according to the
חכמים chachamim we actually don't have those concerns. Okay, I slightly simplified
the תוספות, Tosafot, there are some more nuances to work out but
that's the basic thrust of תוספות's Tosafot answer, which actually is, I
think a little bit relieving for those of us that were a
little having a little angst about this whole גמרא. Gemara Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara, says like this. Okay, but now the גמרא
Gemara, is going to question whether that's really the debate. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, ממאי, mimai, how do you know that's
what they're debating about whether we're concerned about these acts of bestiality?
דילמא דכולי עלמא לא חיישינן. dilma d'kulei alma lo chayshinan. Now it's
very interesting, the first move of the גמרא Gemara, is to say
everybody would say we're not concerned with acts of bestiality, נוך בעסער.
noch besser. Okay, so if everybody would say we're not concerned, so
לא חיישינן לרביעה, lo chayshinan l'reviah, so why does רבי אליעזר Rabi
Eliezer say don't buy it?
והכא
היינו טעמא דרבי אליעזר, ve'hacha hainu ta'ama d'Rabi Eliezer, here's his reasoning,
כדיהודה אמר רב דאמר יהודה אמר רב, kedehuda amar Rav damar Yehuda
amar Rav, he placed on the
cow even a bundle of sacks, פוסלה, paslah, you invalidate it because
it says אשר לא עלה עליה עול asher lo ala aleha ol
that no yoke has gone on it. So according to according to...
It means that even if something that wasn't to do like any
serious work or to pull any burden, it was just you just
rested some sack on it, okay, you've invalidated it. Okay, ובעגלה u-ve'agala
but for an עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa or עגלה, agala, no, עגלה,
Egla, right? עגלה agala is a wagon, right? עגלה. Egla. ובעגלה u-ve'agala
עד שתמשוך בה. ad shetimshoch bah. By an עגלה Egla it says
אשר לא משכה בעול. asher lo mashcha be'ol. So it's not enough
that the burden is on it, it has to pull the burden.
Anyway, so עגלה, Egla, I suggested ערופה.
Arufa. I said עגלה ערופה.
Egla Arufa. Yeah, yeah. So anyway, so what do you call it?
So okay, so therefore, so who needs an act of bestiality? It
would become invalid just if somebody put a little sack on it.
So מר סבר חיישינן, mar savar chaishinan, so everybody would say we're
not concerned about bestiality. It's pretty amazing, up until now we've all
been concerned about bestiality, now nobody is concerned about that. The only
concern is, did they put, did they maybe put a sack on
it for a minute? מר סבר חיישינן ומר סבר לא חיישינן. mar
savar chaishinan u-mar savar lo chaishinan. So maybe that's the debate. So
הגמרא ha-Gemara says no, לא סלקא דעתך. lo salka datach. That doesn't
make sense. משום הנאה פורתא לא מפסיד טובא. mishum hana'a purta lo
mafsid tuva. If the non-Jew has born into his, into his, amongst
his animals a פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, he is not going to,
he is not going to say oh, I'll get one minute's use
out of it by putting something on it, a dollar, a little
tiny little benefit and he'd be afraid that somebody would find out
and he would, it'd be worth tens of hundreds of thousands of
dollars or whatever it would be. So he's going to be too
smart, so that we don't have to be afraid of. But we
do have to be afraid of acts of bestiality. So הגמרא ha-Gemara
says why? Same question. הכא נמי לימא משום הנאה פורתא לא מפסיד
טובא. hacha nami leima mishum hana'a purta lo mafsid tuva. Just for
a little benefit he's not going to lose the value of this
פרה אדומה. Para Aduma. No, התם יצרו תוקפו. hatam yitzro tokfo. No,
there his יצר הרע yetzer hara gets the better of it. It's
so funny, what, he doesn't have another animal if he needs to
do it? דווקא davka this one he's particularly attracted to? Okay, anyway.
So הגמרא ha-Gemara so that's why we can't say they're debating whether
you put a little burden on it, everybody would assume you don't
put a burden on it. The only way to explain their debate
is whether we're concerned of acts of bestiality. But this concern of
those acts is a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer concern, it's not a
חכמים Chachamim concern. So now הגמרא ha-Gemara says one minute, ודילמא דכולי
עלמא לא חיישינן לרבי. u-dilma dechulei alma lo chaishinan lerabi. Again, what's
great about this
גמרא, Gemara for me at least, is that it wants to say
everybody holds we're not concerned about these acts as opposed to yesterday
where everybody was concerned. Maybe here everybody agrees we're not concerned for
these acts. So then what's the reason to not get the פרה
אדומה Para Aduma from the non-Jew? ולהכא היינו טעמא דרבי אליעזר, u-lehacha
hinu ta'ama de-Rabbi Eliezer, here's his reasoning. כדתני שילה, ki-detani Shila,
like שילה Shila taught. דתני שילה, detani Shila, מה טעמא דרבי אליעזר?
ma ta'ama de-Rabbi Eliezer? What's רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's reasoning? דברו אל
בני ישראל ויקחו אליך פרה אדומה תמימה daber el bnei yisrael veyikchu
elecha para aduma tmima etc. So בני ישראל יקחו ואין עובדי כוכבים
יקחו. bnei yisrael yikchu ve'ein ovdei kochavim yikchu. It's based on a
verse. You can only get the פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, buy it
from a Jew, you can't buy it from a non-Jew. No, so
maybe that's his reasoning. That certainly sounds like it would be his
reasoning and then nobody would have to be concerned about bestiality. So
הגמרא ha-Gemara says no, לא סלקא דעתך. lo salka datach. That doesn't
make sense. דקתני סיפא de-katani seifa וכן היה רבי אליעזר פוסל בכל
הקרבנות כולן. ve-chen haya Rabbi Eliezer posel be-chol ha-korbanot kulan.
He actually said you can't buy any animals from non-Jews to use
as sacrifices, which is exactly against the ברייתא Braita yesterday. The ברייתא
Braita said you can buy animals for sacrifices to use as sacrifices,
and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you can't. So obviously, it is
clearly a debate whether you can or cannot buy animals to use
as sacrifice. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you can't and that's
not based on a verse because there's no verse like בני ישראל
bnei yisrael like there is by the פרה אדומה. Para Aduma. ואי
סלקא דעתך כדתני שילה, ve-i salka datach ki-detani Shila, and if it
was based just on a verse, so בשלמא פרה כתיב בה קיחה
bishlama para ktiv ba kicha by a פרה para it says take
this from בני ישראל. bnei yisrael. אלא כולהו קרבנות קיחה כתיב בהו?
ela kuleihu korbanot kicha ktiv behu?
It doesn't say that by the other sacrifices. So now what we
have is a משנה Mishna that says don't leave it in the
stables, a ברייתא Braita that says you can buy them for sacrifices,
and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you can't buy them for sacrifices.
So now what we're saying is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is the
one who's concerned about bestiality. So he would say don't buy for
sacrifices, don't leave it in the stables. But the חכמים Chachamim would
say we're not concerned about these acts, so you can buy it
for sacrifices and maybe you could also leave it in the stables.
Okay, so now הגמרא ha-Gemara says one minute, ודילמא התם הוא דפליגי
רבנן עליה דרבי אליעזר אלא בפרה דדמי יקרא. u-dilma hatam hu de-paligi
rabanan alei de-Rabbi Eliezer ela be-para de-damei yakira. Wait, says the גמרא,
Gemara
you can't, how can you extrapolate from the fact that the rabbis
let you buy a פרה אדומה Para Aduma from the non-Jew that
they're not concerned for acts of bestiality in general? Maybe that's only
by a פרה אדומה Para Aduma that they say this guy won't
risk this very expensive פרה. para. That's a special case where we're
not concerned about it. אבל בשאר קרבנות מודי ליה. aval bi-shear korbanot
modei leh. Maybe they would agree don't buy other animals. Maybe other
animals we have to be concerned because it's not a big loss.
ואלא, ve-ela, so the גמרא Gemara says that can't be because we
know there's an opinion that says it's okay to buy animals for
other sacrifices. דהא דתניא לוקחים מהם בהמה לקרבן, de-ha de-tanya lokchim me-hem
behema le-korban, but we got a ברייתא Braita which we did yesterday.
You can buy an animal
from
them to use as a קרבן. korban. So מני, mani, who's that
go like? לא רבי אליעזר ולא רבנן. lo Rabbi Eliezer ve-lo rabanan.
So according to you, it's nobody. So basically what we have is,
right, we have one, we have one משנה that says don't, no,
don't, don't put in stable.
you know, your animal in the stable. And we have one says
you can buy for קרבן, korban, okay? So then and now we've
got a we've right, and we've got we've got who is this?
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, right, who says don't buy for
פרה parah or קרבן. korban. Okay? So he says don't buy for
פרה parah or קרבן. korban. So somebody's arguing on him. Somebody is
saying you can buy not just buy for a פרה parah which
is expensive and they wouldn't waste it, but you can even buy
for a קרבן. korban. So since we see that they're debating here
whether you can buy for a קרבן korban or not and it's
not limited to פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, so says the גמרא, Gemara
maybe that also this position of even לכתחילה lechatchila not putting it
in the stable is only a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer position. And
maybe the rabbis who say you can buy for a קרבן korban
would also say even לכתחילה lechatchila you can put in the stable,
and the rabbis are not concerned for bestiality and it's only רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who's concerned for bestiality. Okay, so here we're not
distinguishing between לכתחילה lechatchila and בדיעבד, bedieved, right? That was the גמרא's
Gemara initial question. So if you make it if you say or
between our animal and their animal, all those distinctions yesterday we're not
going into. We're saying how do we explain the evidence not by
distinguishing between לכתחילה lechatchila בדיעבד, bedieved, our animal their animal, we explain
the evidence by a debate. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is concerned for
it, so he's concerned here. The rabbis who are not concerned for
buying for קרבן, korban, they probably they wouldn't be concerned for for
keeping your animal in the stable either. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues. So as I said, this is a very nice place
to end, which it sort of says according to the חכמים Chachamim
we're not concerned with this and תוספות basically says that we have
to that it's because of the חכמים Chachamim that we nowadays, says
תוספות, can leave our animals in the stables and so on. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואלא הא דתניא, Ve'ala
ha de'tanya, that which we taught in the ברייתא, baraita, לוקחים מהן
בהמה לקרבן, lokchim meihen behemah lekorban, and I just I just said
that. והא תניא בהדיא, Ve'otanya bahedya, and we also taught explicitly, מאי
אותיבוהו חברוהי mai otivulei chavuroi לרבי אליעזר, leRabbi Eliezer,
what did the colleagues respond to רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? What did
רבי אליעזר's, Rabbi Eliezer you know, בר פלוגתות, bar plugtas, you know,
interlocutors, I think. Anyway, what did they respond to him?
כל צאן קדר יקבצו לך, Kol tzon Keidar yikabtsu lach,
all of the flock of Kedar, which is, you know, ישמעאל, Ishmael,
right? So all of the flock of the Ishmaelites, of the Arabs
or whatever, will be gathered to you to be brought as a
קרבן, korban, יעלו על רצון מזבחי, ya'alu al ratzon lemizbechi, they'll be
brought for desire on my on my altar. So you see, they
say look, you can use the animals of the non-Jews as sacrifices.
So that's the rabbis and that's the debate of the rabbis and
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
One minute. עד כאן לא פליגי אלא בחששא. Ad kan lo pligi
ela bechashasha. So now okay, now the גמרא Gemara says fine, good,
we got it, we got it. It's the debate, this whole thing
is a debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and חכמים, Chachamim, and
the חכמים Chachamim are saying we're not we're not afraid to buy
for קרבן korban and presumably and תוספות discusses the details of this,
but the simple reading of the גמרא Gemara is that presumably it
means that we're not even concerned at all for acts of bestiality
and go ahead and leave your animals in their barns and in
their stables, not a problem. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to
explore this idea that an act of bestiality would invalidate a פרה
אדומה, Para Aduma, because we know it invalidates a קרבן. korban. Okay,
that's learned from, that's a classic מדרש, midrash, which it says what's
the פסוק? pasuk? What's the פסוק pasuk about מן הצאן קרבנו. min
hatzon korbano. מן הצאן ולא כל הצאן. Min hatzon velo kol hatzon.
From the flock and not all the flock. And that is is
learned to exclude animals that were worshipped or designated for עבודה זרה
avoda zara or that were engaged in acts of bestiality and so
on. That we know from a פסוק, pasuk, a classic דרשה drasha
on a פסוק pasuk about קרבנות. korbanot. But the גמרא Gemara says
how do we know that an act of bestiality would invalidate a
פרה אדומה? Para Aduma? Because a פרה אדומה Para Aduma is not
a קרבן. korban. פרה אדומה Para Aduma is very strange, right? You
sanctify it, you slaughter it, you sprinkle the blood towards the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but you do it out of the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. So it has this very weird status. Is it like
a קרבן korban or not like a קרבן? korban? So assuming it's
not like a קרבן, korban, why should an act of bestiality invalidate
it? Okay, so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. עד כאן
לא פליגי אלא בחששא, Ad kan lo pligi ela bechashasha, only if
there's a concern. אבל היכא דודאי רבעה, Aval heicha devadai riva, if
definitely he did an act of bestiality, פסלה, pasra, it invalidated it.
שמע מינה, Shma mina, now should we infer from this, דפרה קדשי
מזבח היא, deparah kodshei mizbeach hi, that the level of the sanctity
of a פרה אדומה Para Aduma although it's not brought as a
קרבן korban is effectively the sanctity of a sacrifice, of something that
could be brought to the altar. And because it's the same type
of a sanctity as if it were a sacrifice, the same way
this act invalidates something as a sacrifice, it invalidates it as a
פרה אדומה. Para Aduma. Okay, it somehow compromises its sanctity and invalidates
it. Okay, so that maybe what we should infer, that that's its
status as if it were a sacrifice. דאי קדשי בדק הבית היא,
De'ei kodshei bedek habayis hi, if it's just treated as something that's
sanctified for the temple, but for the temple ownership, not necessarily for
a sacrificial purposes, if we don't look at it as a type
of a sacrifice. מי מיפסלה ברביעה, mi mipsala b'revia, since when would
an act of bestiality, let's say somebody sanctifies their horse to be
used
for the כהנים kohanim to ride home on or something like that,
and an act of bestiality was done to it? They could still
use it, right? If something could still be used for temple purposes
if it's not a sacrifice, so just because an act of bestiality
was done, so doesn't this prove that a פרה אדומה parah adumah
has a sacrifice-like status? Okay? דאיכא דבדק הבית מי מיפסלה ברביעה, deika
d'bedek habayis mi mipsala b'revia, if it was only just for the
temple without being a sacrifice, this act wouldn't invalidate. So the גמרא
Gemara says no. שאני פרה דחטאת קריה רחמנא. shani parah d'chatas karya
rachmana. The גמרא Gemara, wants to have it both ways. The גמרא
Gemara. sort of says the sanctity is not sacrificial sanctity because it's
not a sacrifice, but the תורה Torah says when it refers to
it, למי נדה חטאת היא. l'mei niddah chatas hi. It uses the
word חטאת chatas by a פרה אדומה, parah adumah, a sin offering.
So what the גמרא Gemara says is there are some ways, it's
like, it seems like splitting hairs, imagine that, the גמרא Gemara seems
like splitting hairs. But it says like the sanctity is generic temple
sanctity, not sacrifice sanctity. But because it's called a חטאת, chatas, the
things that invalidate a חטאת chatas would also invalidate it. For other
purposes, there are other ways in which the sanctity matters that's not
about things that invalidate. So for those other types of things where
sanctity matters, it's not treated as a sacrifice. But when it comes
to invalidating things, we give it, we treat it like we would
a sacrifice because of this word חטאת. chatas. And that's why this
act invalidates it. Okay? חטאת קריה רחמנא, chatas karya rachmana, the תורה
Torah calls it a חטאת. chatas. אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, says the
גמרא, Gemara fine, but if you want to concede that it is,
that it has all the same invalidities as a sacrifice and that's
why this act invalidates it, let me ask you a question, says
the גמרא. Gemara, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata,
I lost my place. אלא מעתה תיפסל ביוצא דופן. ela me'ata tipsal
b'yotzei dofen. We shouldn't be able to use a פרה אדומה parah
adumah that was born by C-section because a C-section animal can't be
used as a sacrifice. Okay? Because I think it says, כי שור
או כשב או עז כי יולד. ki shor o chesev o ez
ki yivaled. So יולד yivaled is understood to be natural birth, not
C-section. And so since that's true by sacrifices that animals have to
be vaginal birth, so if you're going to say that it has
the same status when it comes to questions of validity and invalidity,
maybe for other things not like a sacrifice but for things that
validated or invalidated it, then why can you use a פרה אדומה
parah adumah that was born by C-section? וכי תימא הכי נמי, v'chi
teima hachi nami, maybe you can't. No. אלמא תניא ותניא ברייתא. almah
tanya v'tanya beraisa. הקדישה ביוצא דופן, hikdishah b'yotzei dofen, you sanctified this
thing as a פרה אדומה parah adumah and it was a C-section,
פסולה, psula, it's invalid. So according to the חכמים chachamim actually that
does fit, it's invalid. But we want to understand רבי שמעון's Rabbi
Shimon position. רבי שמעון מכשיר, Rabbi Shimon machshir, but רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says it's okay. So meaning what the גמרא Gemara is saying
is like this: if the various things that invalidate sacrifices invalidate פרה
אדומה, parah adumah, we understand bestiality, we understand C-section according to the
חכמים, chachamim, but why does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say C-section is
okay? Okay, now we have actually a very good reason. רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon in general isn't so bothered with C-sections.
וכי תימא רבי שמעון לטעמיה, v'chi teima Rabbi Shimon l'taameih, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon goes according to his reasoning, דאמר יוצא דופן ולד מעליא
הוא. d'amar yotzei dofen velad maalya hu. He does not give a
different status to something by a C-section. Classic example for this would
be if a woman gives birth by C-section she does not have
the טומאה tumah of a יולדת, yoledes, the impurity of a woman
who has given birth, right? The תורה Torah says אשה כי תזריע
וילדה זכר וטמאה שבעת ימים isha ki tazria v'yalda zachar v'tam'a shivas
yamim etcetera. So the rabbis say עד שילדה ממקום שמזרעת, ad sheyalda
mimakom shemazraas, only if she gives birth from the place where the
seed comes forth, meaning only if she does vaginal birth. ורבי שמעון
v'Rabbi Shimon says no, even
C-section that פרשה parsha applies to her. So the גמרא Gemara says
maybe רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon general position, he just does not distinguish
in any area of הלכה between C-section and vaginal birth. So what
about בכור? bechor? בכור bechor is interesting, right? Would it be פטר
רחם peter rechem and so on? I don't know. So we'd have
to look at that. But for now let's just assume as a
general point of departure. So therefore it works out. Normal things that
invalidate sacrifices invalidate פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So that's bestiality, that's C-section,
but רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says C-section is never a problem. Okay,
let's say we would try to say that. והאמר רבי יוחנן, v'ha'amar
Rabbi Yochanan, maybe that could work, but it doesn't work based on
what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. Because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
מודה היה רבי שמעון לעניין קדשים שאינו קדוש. modeh hayah Rabbi Shimon
l'inyan kodashim she'eino kadosh. That for whatever reason it's not like he
says C-section is always the same. Even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would
agree when it came to sacrifices you can't use an animal born
by C-section. Okay, so now we got a problem. If רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says that by normal sacrifices you can't use such an
animal, why does he say it's okay by a פרה אדומה? parah
adumah? It seems to be that at least according to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon normal invalidities don't apply to a פרה אדומה. parah adumah.
So how do we understand what this is all about? So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, אלא ela fine, let's go this way.
שאני פרה הואיל ומום פוסל בה דבר ערווה ועבודה זרה פוסל בה.
shani parah ho'il umom posel bah davar ervah v'avodah zarah posel bah.
Maybe according to the חכמים chachamim you're right. According to the חכמים...
chachamim... either because it's called a חטאת chatas or maybe even because
it's according to the חכמים, Chachamim, maybe it has קדושת מזבח. kedushas
mizbeach. So everything invalidates, you know, it what, what do you call
it? בשארי B'sha'ari invalidates, C-sections invalidate, it's just like a קורבן. korban.
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon though is different. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says
I don't treat it like a קורבן. korban. Normal things would not
invalidate. However, the תורה Torah does say by the פרה אדומה parah
adumah that it has to be תמימה, temimah, right? It has to
be unblemished. One thing we know about a פרה אדומה parah adumah
is that a מום mum invalidates. Normal things for a sacrifice, not
a problem, it's not a sacrifice. But מום mum invalidates. And you
know what says רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon? There are things that are
considered to be like a מום mum even though they're not a
physical blemish. If you would, they're a religious blemish. Okay? So there's
other, the only thing that invalidates for a פרה אדומה parah adumah
other than the yoke is the blemish, but the definition of blemish
is a little bit broader than physical blemish. Okay? So he says
הואיל ומום פוסל בה, hoil umum posol bah, since a physical blemish
invalidates, דבר ערווה ועבודה זרה פוסל בה, davar ervah ve'avoda zarah posol
bah, an act of forbidden sex or an act of idolatry if
it was worshipped also invalidates. דכתיב כי משחתם בהם מום בם. dechsiv
ki moshchasam bahem mum bam. עבודה זרה Avoda zarah no, דכתיב, dechsiv,
okay, it says that they're, what do you call it, their corruption
is in them, their blemish is in them. ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל,
vesana devei Rebbi Yishmael, כל מקום שנאמר השחתה, kol makom shene'emar hashchasa,
so that verse
identifies corruption with blemish. So and what does corruption mean? השחתה Hashchasa
means אינו אלא דבר ערווה ועבודה זרה. eino ella davar ervah ve'avoda
zarah. The word להשחית lehashchis can refer to a sexual perversion and
עבודה זרה, avoda zarah, a perversion of worship. Okay. דבר ערווה דכתיב
כי השחית כל בשר את דרכו על הארץ, Davar ervah dechsiv ki
hishchis kol basar es darko al ha'aretz, all flesh had perverted its
way, and the classic rabbinic interpretation of the sin of that generation
was acts of bestiality. Okay. עבודה זרה דכתיב, Avoda zarah dechsiv,
and that exactly matches פן תשחיתון, pen tashchisun, lest you act corruptly,
ועשיתם לכם פסל, va'asisem lachem pesel, and you make for yourself an
idol. Okay, so עבודה זרה avoda zarah and acts of forbidden sexuality
are considered a corruption of your way, a corruption of divine worship,
and they're considered to create a type of a blemish on the
animal. So it's a very interesting answer. It's not some generic status
as a sacrifice. Specifically this is a type of a blemish. And
that's why the act of bestiality is a problem. Okay? והא פרה,
veha parah, and this פרה אדומה, parah adumah, הואיל ומום פוסל בה,
hoil umum posol bah, we know that a blemish invalidates it, דבר
ערווה ועבודת כוכבים פוסל בה, davar ervah ve'avodas kochavim posol bah, so
an act of idol worship or an act of sexuality, of bestiality
also invalidates. Okay. One last piece. Look at this. You didn't think
we were going to finish the דף today, did you? גופא, Gufa,
I didn't. תני שילא. Tani Shila. שילא Shila taught. מאי טעמא דרבי
אליעזר? Mai ta'ama deRebbi Eliezer? What's the reason of רבי אליעזר? Rebbi
Eliezer? דכתיב דבר אל בני ישראל ויקחו, dechsiv daber el benei Yisrael
veyikchu, בני ישראל יקחו ואין עובדי כוכבים יקחו. Benei Yisrael yikchu ve'ein
ovdei kochavim yikchu.
So this is going back to saying not a generic problem with
buying the animals even not פרה אדומה parah adumah because of concerns
of bestiality, that we sort of said. But here it's anchoring it
specifically by פרה אדומה parah adumah in this verse of get it
from בני ישראל Benei Yisrael and not from the non-Jews. Okay? So
that's bracketing the whole bestiality issue. אלא מעתה, Ella me'ata, says the
גמרא, Gemara but if that's true, if we're going to take that
to mean you can only buy it from Jews, דבר אל בני
ישראל ויקחו לי תרומה. daber el benei Yisrael veyikchu li teruma. This
is coming up, right? So here you go, perfect דרשה drasha for
next שבת. Okay. So speak to בני ישראל Benei Yisrael and take
for me a תרומה. teruma. So what, does that mean we only
take donations from Jews, not from non-Jews? הכי נמי דבני ישראל יקחו
ואין עובדי כוכבים יקחו? Hachi nami debenei Yisrael yikchu ve'ein ovdei kochavim
yikchu?
We can't take donations from non-Jews to use for temple purposes? All
right, so tell that to all these rabbis who are trying to
do fundraising or whatever, you can only, can't ask a non-Jew. Anyway.
וכי תימא הכי נמי, Vechi seima hachi nami, yeah maybe, maybe we
don't accept any donations from non-Jews for our temple. Okay, so one
minute. והאמר רבי יהודה אמר שמואל, Veha'amar Rebbi Yehuda amar Shmuel, famous
story from קידושין. Kiddushin. שאלו את רבי אליעזר. Sha'alu es Rebbi Eliezer.
They asked רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, עד היכן כיבוד אב ואם? Ad
heichan kibud av va'em? How far does כיבוד אב ואם kibud av
va'em go? What would be like some ideal to reach for in
terms of כיבוד אב ואם? kibud av va'em? אמר להן צאו וראו
מה עשה עובד כוכבים אחד. Amar lahen tze'u ur'u mah asah oved
kochav ehad. Go see what this particular non-Jew did לאביו באשקלון, la'aviv
be'Ashkelon, for his father in Ashkelon. Like even a non-Jew, you know,
who's not obligated in כיבוד אב ואם, kibud av va'em, will serve
as a model because of, like, it's such an ethics and a
morality that you don't necessarily, it's an interesting question, like, what do
we mean by using this as a model? Like, to sort of
speak about the fact about the deep sort of morality that is
at the core of this, even beyond the fact of commandment. So
go take a look, and this can serve as our model. Okay.
ודמא בן נתינה שמו. Udama ben Nesina shemo. His name was דמא
בן נתינה. Dama ben Nesina. פעם אחת ביקשו ממנו אבנים לאפוד. Pa'am
ahas bikshu mimenu avanim la'eifod.
They wanted to buy for him, you know, precious jewels for the
אפוד, eifod, בשישים ריבוא, beshishim ribo,
and they were going to pay 600,000 whatever דינרי dinarei שכר, sachar,
as a compensation. רב כהנא מתני בשמונים ריבוא, Rav Kahana masni beshmonim
ribo,
800,000. והיו מפתחות מונחות תחת מראשותיו של אביו. Vehayu maftechos munachos tachas
merashosav shel aviv. And the keys to the warehouse were under his
father's head. ולא ציערו. Velo tzi'aro. And he didn't wake up his
father. Now of course what's so funny is that, you know, every
Everybody says, oh probably his father would have wanted to be woken
up so he wouldn't lose the deal, which is why the interesting
thing comes why these stories of how far does it go sometimes
they are like you know they are like these these extreme stories
and then when the פוסקים Poskim say but that's not really the
הלכה like if the father would have wanted to be awoken up
of course you should have awoken him up. But anyway but whatever
we're going to assume his father wouldn't have wanted to be woken
up anyway but here's the problem the אבני אפוד Avnei Ephod is
in that פסוק posuk וזאת התרומה אשר תקחו מאיתם זהב וכסף ונחושת
ותכלת וארגמן ותולעת שני ושש ועזים ועורת אילם מאדמים ועורת תחשים ועצי
שטים שמן למאר ובשמים לשמן המשחה ולקטרת הסמים אבני שהם Vezos haterumah
asher tichu me'itam zahav vakesef unechoshet utcheiles ve'argaman vesola'as shani vesheish ve'izim
ve'orot eilim me'odamim ve'orot tichashim va'atzei shitim shemen lamo'or ubesamim leshemen hamishcha
uliktoret hasamim avnei shoham אבני שהם avnei shoham ואבני
מלאים. ve'avnei milu'im. So the אבני מלאים avnei milu'im are the אבני
אפוד avnei ephod and here they are buying it from a non-Jew
so you see it's okay so how would you know so how
would and would what do you call it this is the same
what do you call it right this is the same רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer the same רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says don't buy
a פרה אדומה parah adumah from a non-Jew is the רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer that says they bought the אבני אפוד avnei ephod from
this non-Jew so how do you explain that. So the גמרא Gemara
says אבני שהם הפסיק העניין avnei shoham hifsik ha'inyan no because it
doesn't have a ו vav right וזאת התרומה אשר תקחו מאיתם זהב
וכסף ונחושת ותכלת וארגמן ותולעת שני ושש ועזים vezos haterumah asher tichu
me'itam zahav vakesef unechoshet utcheiles ve'argaman vesola'as shani vesheish ve'izim but then
it says אבני שהם avnei shoham there's no ו. vav. So it
says and when it says דבר אל בני ישראל daber el bnei
Yisrael אל בני ישראל el bnei Yisrael ויקחו לי תרומה veyikchu li
terumah right ויקחו לי veyikchu li so it's only בני ישראל bnei
Yisrael and then it's זהב וכסף ונחושת zahav vakesef unechoshet
זהב וכסף ונחושת zahav vakesef unechoshet ו ו ו ו ו ו
vav vav vav vav vav vav
and then it says אבני שהם avnei shoham there's no ו vav
and then it says ואבני מלאים. ve'avnei milu'im. So what it says
is and the אבני מלאים avnei milu'im are the אבני אפוד avnei
ephod okay so you're limited to get from בני ישראל bnei Yisrael
all of this stuff but since there's no ו vav from this
point on you can get from the non-Jews okay but the גמרא
does not like this answer. The גמרא says והא ואבני מלאים כתיב
דהדר ערביה veha ve'avnei milu'im kesiv dahadar arbeih דהדר ערביה dahadar arbeih
but this ו vav still links it all the way down okay
so don't give me a break says the גמרא okay this this
is included and if this is limiting to בני ישראל bnei Yisrael
then explain to me why you were able to buy those אבני
אפוד avnei ephod from this non-Jew. So the גמרא says okay so
you know what I'm going to leave you with that cliffhanger okay
so we want to know how does רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who
says you can't buy a פרה אדומה parah adumah from non-Jews because
it says דבר אל בני ישראל daber el bnei Yisrael you know
what's the פסוק pasuk it says ויקחו אליך דבר אל בני ישראל
ויקחו אליך
vayikchu eilecha daber el
bnei Yisrael veyikchu eilecha
if you can't get a פרה אדומה parah adumah from a non-Jew
how can you get the אבני אפוד avnei ephod from a non-Jew
it seems like it should be the same issue okay so I'm
going to leave you with that cliffhanger and we will pick it
up.